<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>saccades | R. Calen Walshe</title>
    <link>/tags/saccades/</link>
      <atom:link href="/tags/saccades/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>saccades</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/img/icon-192.png</url>
      <title>saccades</title>
      <link>/tags/saccades/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Modelling saccades</title>
      <link>/project/saccades/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/saccades/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Saccadic eye movements are the primary vehicle by which human gaze is brought in alignment with vital visual information present in naturalistic scenes. Although numerous studies using the double-step paradigm have demonstrated that saccade preparation is subject to modification under certain conditions, this has yet to be studied directly within a naturalistic scene-viewing context. To reveal characteristic properties of saccade programming during naturalistic scene viewing, we contrasted behavior across three conditions. In the Static condition of the main experiment, double-step targets were presented following a period of stable fixation on a central cross. In a Scene condition, targets were presented while participants actively explored a naturalistic scene. During a Noise condition, targets were presented during active exploration of a 1/f noise-filtered scene. In Experiment 2, we measure saccadic responses in three Static conditions (Uniform, Scene, and Noise) in which the backgrounds are the same as Experiment 1 but scene exploration is no longer permitted. We find that the mechanisms underlying saccade modification generalize to both dynamic conditions. However, we show that a property of saccade programming known as the saccadic dead time (SDT), the interval prior to saccade onset during which a saccade may not be canceled or modified, is lower in the Static task than it is in the dynamic tasks. We also find a trend toward longer SDT in the Scene as compared with Noise conditions. We discuss the implication of these results for computational models of scene viewing, reading, and visual search tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walshe, R.C. &amp;amp; Nuthmann, A. (2015). Mechanisms of saccadic decision making while encoding naturalistic scenes. Journal of Vision, 15(21).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Walshe, R.C. &amp;amp; Nuthmann, A. (2014). Asymmetric control of fixation durations in scene viewing. Vision Research, 100, 38-46.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
